Finding Aid for Native American Studies Program (University of Michigan) records, 1972-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Native American Studies Program (University of Michigan) records 1972-2003
University of Michigan. Native American Studies Program.
0.75 linear feet
2010213 Bimu 2
The Native American studies began at the University of Michigan in 1972. In 1983 it was formalized as a program within the Program in American Culture. Records include material relating to the establishment and growth of the Native American Studies Program. Collection contains records relating to the Committee on Native American Studies, focusing particularly on the early planning and implementation of the Native American Studies Program and course information, documentation of campus cultural activities, and issues of the Native American Advocate.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Materials were received from the University of Michigan Native American Studies program in August 2010 (Donor # 10395 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open without restriction.
The University of Michigan's Native American Studies Program was conceived in the early seventies, following several years of lobbying on the part of the University's Native Americans students, as well as local Native Americans. Anthony L. Genia, was hired in 1972 as a Native American recruiter in the admissions office, and was primarily concerned with establishing a Native American program at the University. The University of Michigan Native American Student Association (UM-NASA) was established around the same time, holding its first organizational meeting on November 13, 1972. A Native American Advocate, Charles "Moose" Pamp, was hired by the UM Office of Special Services. He was to serve as "an aggressive exponent for Native American concerns throughout the campus and community," and would "open up new channels of communication...and actively represent Native American interests." (Native American Advocate, November 1972)
It was not until 1983 that the Native American Studies Program was officially established within the Program in American Culture. Since its inception, the Native American Studies Program at the University of Michigan has implemented several courses each year, including those in Ojibwe language instruction. There are several Native American student groups operating at the University as well, including American Indians at the University of Michigan, The Circle, the American Indian Science Engineering Society, the Native American Law Students Association, and the Native Caucus. These groups actively sponsor speakers and other events, and have put on an annual April Dance for Mother Earth Pow Wow in conjunction with the local Native community since 1972.
The records largely document the inception and early years of the University of Michigan's Native American Studies Program, beginning in 1972, as well as cultural and financial material from more recent years. The collection is arranged in a single series, Topical Files.
Two folders contain extensive information regarding the Ojibwa language courses, which have been offered regularly since 1973. The majority of documents relate to the growth of the program, specifically the expansion of Native American course offerings, the hiring of Native American faculty members, the dialogue between Native American students and the University over demands for a cultural center, and increased support services on campus for Native American Students.
The collection also consists of various budget and financial documents, as well as grant proposals. Several issues of a student publication, the Native American Advocate from 1972-1973, are included, in addition to non-University publications relating to Native American issues.
Subjects:
Indians of North America--Michigan--Higher education.; Minorities--Education (higher)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Native American Student Association.; University of Michigan. Native American Studies Program.
- Topical Files
  - Budget and Grant Proposals Native American Orientation Program (Box 1)
  - Budget and Finances Victor Masayesva and Gerald Vizenore Film Series, 1991-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Committee on Native American Studies, 1972-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Cultural Center, 1975 (Box 1)
  - E-mails (print-out), Memos, and Advertisements, 1995-2000 (Box 1)
  - Faculty (Native American) 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - LSA Mini-Course, Native American Political and Social Problems, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Native American Advocate, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Native American Courses, 1972-1978 (Box 1)
  - Native American Programs outside of UM, 1972-1986 (Box 1)
  - Ojibwa Language Courses, 1973-2002, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Proposals for Pre-and Post-Doctorate Native American Scholars Program, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Publications regarding Native American issues, 1972-1973, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Supportive Native American Services on campus (Advocate, Counselor, Admissions), 1973-1975, 1992 (Box 1)
  - UM Campus Cultural Activities, 1973-2003, 2 folders (Box 1)